

João Pedro Dias

Engineer. Developer. Researcher. Amateur photographer.

Porto, Portugal

☑ jpmdias@fe.up.pt | ♠ jpdias.me | ☑ jpdias | ் joaopdias | У jpd1as | ⑤ jpdias

Summary.

Current Researcher at INESC TEC and pursuing a PhD degree in Informatics Engineering. Graduated from the Integrated Masters in Informatics and Computing Engineering, I'm passionate about technology, with a special focus on security and privacy, web development, data mining & Internet of Things. Besides that, I'm also an amateur photographer, football player, book lover and science addict.

ORCiD: 0000-0001-9066-6436 | Personal Page: https://jpdias.me

Education _

Doctoral Program in Informatics Engineering - ProDEI (PhD)

Porto, Portugal

FACULTY OF ENGINEERING OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PORTO (FEUP)

2016-Exp. 2020

· Work under Supervision of Hugo Sereno Ferreira, PhD and Co-Supervision of João Pascoal Faria, PhD

Master in Informatics and Computing Engineering - MIEIC (MSc)

Porto, Portugal

FACULTY OF ENGINEERING OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PORTO (FEUP)

2011-2016

- GPA: 15 out of 20
- Volunteer at Semana Profissão: Engenheiro (SPE) 2014 & 2016

Sciences and Technologies

Amarante, Porto, Portugal

2008-2011

EXTERNATO DE VILA MEÃ
• GPA: 17 out of 20

Work Experience _____

Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto

Campus FEUP, Porto, Portugal

INVITED ASSISTANT LECTURER

Fev. 2017 - Today

 $\bullet \ \ \text{Teaching practical lectures of Operating Systems and Software Development Laboratories}.$

INESC TEC – Institute for Systems and Computer Engineering, Technology and Science | CSIG – Centre for Information Systems and Computer Graphics

Campus FEUP, Porto, Portugal

RESEARCHER

May 2017 – Today

- Researching in the area of Internet of Things, with special focus on Blockchain and Healthcare applications, in the scope of the project NanoSTIMA: *Macro-to-Nano Human Sensing: Towards Integrated Multimodal Health Monitoring and Analytics*.
- Project details: nanostima.inesctec.pt

LIACC - Artificial Intelligence and Computer Science Laboratory

University of Porto, Porto, Portugal

RESEARCHER

Sept. 2016 - Apr. 2017

- Researching data representation and data mining applications on railway transportation systems in the scope of the project PED-DIR: Weigth in Motion and Wheels Defect Detection.
- Technologies: MongoDB, Python and Web Development | Project details: www.peddir.eu & www.in2rail.eu

ShiftForward, S.A. Porto, Portugal

SUMMER ENGINEERING INTERN

Jul. 2015 - Aug. 2015

- Development of a Deploy Logger Service, a service for documenting and recording the release of new product versions over time.
- Technologies: Scala and Backbone.js | Project details: shiftforward.github.io/malamute

Centro Hospitalar do Tâmega e Sousa, E.P.E.

Penafiel, Porto, Portugal

IT DEPARTMENT INTERNSHIP

Jul. 2014 - Aug. 2014

- Development of an expedient management system for replacing the existent system based on paper archives.
- Technologies: MySQL and PHP

JANUARY 16, 2019

INTEGRATED MASTER IN INFORMATICS AND COMPUTING ENGINEERING · FEUP · 5 YEARS

Invited Assistant Lecturer

				2017-2018	2018-2019
		YEAR	ECTS	CLASSES	* Hours
Object Oriented Programming Laboratory	LPOO	2	6	-	1 * 3h
Operating Systems	SOPE	2	6	2 * 2h	1 * 2h
Software Development Laboratory	LDSO	4	7,5	-	1 * 4h
Software Systems Architecture	ASSO	4	6	-	1 * 3h

Publications _____

CONFERENCE ARTICLES (PEER-REVIEWED)

BLOCKCHAIN-BASED PKI FOR CROWDSOURCED IOT SENSOR INFORMATION

Porto, Portugal

Guilherme Pinto, João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2018

14th International Conference on Information Assurance and Security { DOI: To Appear }

A BLOCKCHAIN-BASED SCHEME FOR ACCESS CONTROL IN E-HEALTH SCENARIOS

Porto, Portugal

João Pedro Dias, Hugo Sereno Ferreira and Ângelo Martins

2018

14th International Conference on Information Assurance and Security { DOI: To Appear }

DYNAMIC ALLOCATION OF SERVERLESS FUNCTIONS IN IOT ENVIRONMENTS

Bucharest, Romania

Duarte Pinto, João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2018

16th IEEE International Conference on Embedded and Ubiquitous Computing { DOI: 10.1109/EUC.2018.00008 }

A REACTIVE AND MODEL-BASED APPROACH FOR DEVELOPING INTERNET-OF-THINGS SYSTEMS

Coimbra, Portugal

João Pedro Dias, João Pascoal Faria and Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2018

7th Software Engineering Doctoral Symposium (SEDES 2018) – Part of the 11th International Conference on the Quality of Information and Communications Technology (QUATIC 2018) { DOI: 10.1109/QUATIC.2018.00049 }

A Brief Overview of Existing Tools for Testing the Internet-of-Things

Västerås, Sweden

João Pedro Dias, Flávio Couto, Ana C.R. Paiva, Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2018

First International Workshop on Verification and Validation of Internet of Things (VVIoT 2018) – Part of the 11th IEEE Conference on Software Testing, Validation and Verification (ICST 2018) { DOI: 10.1109/ICSTW.2018.00035 }

PATTERNS FOR THINGS THAT FAIL

Vancouver, Canada

António Ramadas, Gil Domingues, João Pedro Dias, Ademar Aguiar, Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2017

24th Conference on Pattern Languages of Programs (PLoP 2017) { DOI: To Appear } {PDF}

TOWARDS A FRAMEWORK FOR AGENT-BASED SIMULATION OF USER BEHAVIOUR IN E-COMMERCE CONTEXT

Porto, Portugal

DUARTE DUARTE, JOÃO PEDRO DIAS, HUGO SERENO FERREIRA AND ZAF. KOKKINOGENIS

2017

 $15^{th}\ International\ Conference\ on\ Practical\ Applications\ of\ Agents\ and\ Multi-Agent\ Systems\ (PAAMS'17)\ \{\ DOI:\ PAAMS'17\}\ \{\ P$

10.1007/978-3-319-61578-3_3 }

AUTOMATING THE EXTRACTION OF STATIC CONTENT AND DYNAMIC BEHAVIOUR FROM E-COMMERCE WEBSITES

Madeira, Portugal

João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2017

8th International Conference on Ambient Systems, Networks and Technologies (ANT'17) { DOI: 10.1016/j.procs.2017.05.355 }

A HANDS-ON APPROACH ON BOTNETS FOR BEHAVIOR EXPLORATION

Porto, Portugal

João Pedro Dias, José Pedro Pinto and José Magalhães Cruz

2017

2nd International Conference on Internet of Things, Big Data and Security (IoTBDS 2017) { DOI: 10.5220/0006392404630469 }

INFORMAL PUBLICATIONS & OTHERS

A PR	ELIMINARY STUDY ON MESH NETWORKS AND IOT	Porto, Portugal
	Barros, Luis Sousa, João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira	2018
11 th M	eeting of Young Researchers of University of Porto (IJUP 2018)	
Auto	MATING THE EXTRACTION OF STATIC CONTENT AND DYNAMIC BEHAVIOUR FROM	Porto, Portugal
E-Co	MMERCE WEBSITES	r orto, r ortugui
	Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira	2017
10 th M	leeting of Young Researchers of University of Porto (IJUP 2017)	
A HAI	NDS-ON APPROACH ON BOTNETS FOR A LEARNING PURPOSE	Porto, Portugal
	Pedro Dias, José Pedro Pinto and José Magalhães Cruz	2016
9 th Me	eeting of Young Researchers of University of Porto (IJUP 2016)	
Diss	ERTATIONS	
	RSE ENGINEERING STATIC CONTENT AND DYNAMIC BEHAVIOUR OF E-COMMERCE	Porto, Portugal
	S FOR FUN AND PROFIT	2016
	vised by Hugo Sereno Ferreira Grade: 17 out of 20. er's Dissertation, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto { ID: 10216/85374 }	2016
Maste	er's dissertation, ractity of Engineering, offiversity of Forto { ID. 10210/65574 }	
Cor	nference Organization	
2018	Student Volunteer , XP 2018 – 19 th International Conference on Agile Software	Porto, Portugal
	Development	
2018	Conference Organization Chair , DSIE'18 – 13 th Doctoral Symposium in Informatics Engineering	Porto, Portugal
2018	Advisor Board Member , Talk a Bit – Student Organized Techn Conference, 6 th Edition	Porto, Portugal
	(2018)	
2017	Student Volunteer (Media Coverage) , EPIA 2017 – 18 th EPIA Conference on Artificial Intelligence	Porto, Portugal
2017	Web Communication Co-chair , ACM CarSys 2017 – The Second ACM International Workshop on Smart, Autonomous, and Connected Vehicular Systems and Services, part of the The 23 rd Annual International Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking (MobiCom 2017)	Utah, USA
2017	Advisor Board Member, Talk a Bit – Student Organized Tech Conference, 5 th Edition	Porto, Portugal
	(2017)	
2016	Conference Chair, Talk a Bit – Student Organized Tech Conference, 4 th Edition (2016)	Porto, Portugal
2016	Web Communication Co-chair, 2016 IEEE 19th International Conference on Intelligent	Rio de Janeiro, Brazil
	Transportation Systems (ITSC 2016)	
2014	Student Volunteer, Inter-University Programming Marathon (MIUP 2014)	Porto, Portugal
2014	Student Volunteer , INForum - Symposion on Informatics (INForum 2014)	Porto, Portugal
Edu	cational & Scientific Activities	
MAS	ter's Dissertation Co-Supervising	
2017	DYNAMIC ALLOCATION OF SERVERLESS FUNCTIONS IN IOT ENVIRONMENTS by Duarte	Porto, Portugal
2018	Pinto, Supervised by Hugo Sereno Ferreira, PhD, Masters in Informatics and	
	Computing Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto { ID: 10216/114149 }	
2017	BLOCKCHAIN AS A PKI FOR OWNERSHIP CONTROL OF IOT DEVICES by Guilherme Pinto,	Porto, Portugal
2018	Supervised by Hugo Sereno Ferreira, PhD , Masters in Informatics and Computing Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto { ID: 10216/114144 }	
2016	Interoperability In Software Applications For Smart Cities: Towards A	Porto, Portugal
2017	REFERENCE ARCHITECTURE by José Pedro Pinto, Supervised by Rosaldo Rossetti, PhD, Masters in Informatics and Computing Engineering, Faculty of Engineering,	
	University of Porto { ID: 10216/107529 }	

PROGRAM COMMITTEES & REVIEWS

2017	Program Committee (Senior) Member, Talk A Bit – Student Organized Tech	Porto, Portugal
	Conference, 7 th Edition (2019)	
2017	Program Committee Member , IEEE S3C 2017 - 2017 IEEE Summer School on Smart	Natal, Brazil
	Cities	
2017	IEEE Intelligent Vehicles Symposium (IEEE IV'17), Reviewer	California, USA
2017	IEEE 20th International Conference on Intelligent Transportation Systems (IEEE	Yokohama, Japan
	ITSC 2017), Reviewer	

Invited Talks & Workshops

Information Systems and Software Engineering Seminars (SESI & SES)

Lisboa, Portugal

HOSTED AT FACULTY OF ENGINEERING, UNIVERSITY OF PORTO FOR STUDENTS OF THE MIEIC & MESW DEGREES

Sept. 2017

• **Seminar**: How to Kill Your Privacy and IoT Your Home Along the Way.

Pixels Camp 2017

Lisboa, Portugal

HOSTED BY BRIGHT PIXEL AND BETA-I Sept. 2017

• Workshop: PiHeadquarters or How to Take Control of your House with Raspberry Pi and Docker.

OPOSEC Meetup: [0x33] - The Meet Porto, Portugal

HOSTED BY BLIP.PT Apr. 2016

• **Presentation**: A hands-on approach on botnets for a learning purpose.

Share World Seminar 2015 – "Europe vs. Asia: Grass Is Always Greener On The Other Side" FEUP, Porto, Portugal

HOSTED BY SHARE GLOBAL STUDENT THINK TANK

March 2015

• Workshop: How To Create Your First Personal Webpage.

Additional Training _____

2018	1 st UPTEC School on the Future of Computing, UPTEC – Science and Technology Park	FBAUP, Porto, Portugal
	of University of Porto	
2017	CyberTalk: Security - Business Enablement, Multicert - Electronic Certification	FEUP, Porto, Portugal
	Services, S.A.	
2017	Project Management, ERASMUS+ Mobility for teaching	FEUP, Porto, Portugal
2016	AWS Technical Essentials Online, Amazon Web Services – Training and Certification	Online
2015	Practical Workshop in Agile Project Management, Strongstep - Innovation in	UPTEC, Porto, Portugal
	Software Quality	
2015	CERN Spring Campus, CERN - European Organization for Nuclear Research	Lisbon, Portugal
2014	M101JS: MongoDB for Node.js Developers, MongoDB University	Online

Skills & Languages ____

```
Programming
Python ■ Node.JS ■ C/C++ ■ Scala ■ Java ■ C# ■ PHP ■

Web Technologies
HTML5 ■ CSS ■ JavaScript ■ Laravel(PHP) ■ Flask(Python) ■ Bootstrap(CSS) ■ jQuery(JS) ■

Databases
MySQL ■ PostgreSQL ■ InfluxDB ■ MongoDB ■

Arduino ■ Git ■ Android ■ Windows Apps ■ Docker ■ LaTeX ■

Languages
Portuguese (Mother-tongue) ■ English ■
```

Pro Bono Activity _____

EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE (SECRETARY)

ACADEMIC

IEEE University of Porto Student Branch

Porto, Portugal

STUDENT MEMBER

2012 – Today

2013 - 2015

• As a voluntary member I had organized and co-organized some workshops (*C#*, *Photography*, *ET_EX*, *Web Development*) and other events including *IEEE Day*, *IEEEXtreme* and *IEEEmadC*.

• As secretary I was also responsable for mantain the minutes of all meetings and other paperwork.

HUMANITARIAN

Luz da Vida Youth Group

Amarante, Porto, Portugal

FOUNDER MEMBER 2009 – 2011

• Founder and former active member, I had taken part of large number of activities on behalf of the village community.

Honors & Awards _____

INTERNATIONAL

2017	427 th (of 3350), IEEEXtreme – 24h Programming Competition 11.0, <i>ieee.org/xtreme</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2017	847 th (of 2815), Google Hash Code 2017, hashcode.withgoogle.com	Online – Porto, Portugal
2015	189 th (of 2477), IEEEXtreme – 24h Programming Competition 9.0, <i>ieee.org/xtreme</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2014	Honorable Mention , IEEEmadC – Mobile Application Dev. Contest, <i>ieeemadc.org</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2013	126th (of 2570) , IEEEXtreme – 24h Programming Competition 7.0, <i>ieee.org/xtreme</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2013	2nd Place , European BEST Engineering Competition, <i>ebec.best.eu.org</i>	Warsaw, Poland

DOMESTIC

2018	6 th (of 31 Participants), CIBER PERSEU 2018 Portguese Army Exercise – Capture The	Portuguese Military Academy,
	Flag component by diateam, exercito.pt	Lisbon, Portugal
2011	1 st Place, PmatE Mat12 – Mathematics Competition, <i>pmate.ua.pt</i>	University of Aveiro, Portugal
2009	2nd Place , PmatE Fis12 – Physics Competition, <i>pmate.ua.pt</i>	University of Aveiro, Portugal

Interests & Hobbies _____

F.A.D.A. Amateur League

GRUPO DESPORTIVO E RECREATIVO DE TRAVANCA

2016 – 2017

Amateur Photographer

NATURE, LANDSCAPE, URBAN EXPLORATION, EVENTS

- 2018 Finalist at the Norte Multimédia Contest Photography Category
 Promoted by the Norte Portugal Regional Coordination and Development Commission (CCDR-N)
- 2018 Finalist at the PORTUGAL NUM ISQUEIRO BIC® Contest Promoted by the I Love My BIC initiative by BIC Portugal
- 2010 Exposition at Movimento d'Artes, Travanca, Amarante, Portugal Promoted by the Cooperativa Cultural Vinha das Artes

Anywhere 2008 – Today